<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno XIIII. et XV. Henrici VIII. The Kynge our soueraygne lorde Henrye the viij. after the conquest, by the grace of God king of England and of Fraunce and lorde of Irelande, at his parlyamente holden at London, the xv. day of April in the xiiii. yeare of his moste noble reygne: and from thence adiourned to Westminster the last day of Iuly the xv. yeare of his sayde reigne, and there holden to the honour of Almightye God and of holye Churche, and for the wealthe and profytte of thys hys realme, by the assent of the lords spiritual and temporall, [and] the commons in thys presente parliament assembled, [and] by aucthoritye of the same, hath, doo, to be ordeined, made, [and] enacted, certaine statutes and ordynaunces in maner and fourme folowing.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9363.4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121456</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899048</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899048</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176604</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74019)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176604)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 531:1c; 1984:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno XIIII. et XV. Henrici VIII. The Kynge our soueraygne lorde Henrye the viij. after the conquest, by the grace of God king of England and of Fraunce and lorde of Irelande, at his parlyamente holden at London, the xv. day of April in the xiiii. yeare of his moste noble reygne: and from thence adiourned to Westminster the last day of Iuly the xv. yeare of his sayde reigne, and there holden to the honour of Almightye God and of holye Churche, and for the wealthe and profytte of thys hys realme, by the assent of the lords spiritual and temporall, [and] the commons in thys presente parliament assembled, [and] by aucthoritye of the same, hath, doo, to be ordeined, made, [and] enacted, certaine statutes and ordynaunces in maner and fourme folowing.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1575?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
       <!--           <note>Signatures: A&amp;#x2020; B&#x98;.</note> -->
                  <note>Running title reads: Anno XIIII. et XV. Henrici Octaui.</note>
                  <note>In this edition the title page has a border of straight lines.</note>
                  <note>Also appears as part of STC 9304 at reel 531:1c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Peterborough Cathedral, Peterborough, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="report">
            <pb facs="tcp:176604:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176604:1"/>
            <head>ANNO XIIII. ET XV. HENRICI VIII.</head>
            <p>THe Kynge our ſoueraygne lorde Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye the viij. after the conqueſt, by the grace of God king of England and of Fraunce and lorde of Irelande, at his parlyamente holden at London, the xv. day of April in the xiiii. yeare of his moſte noble reygne: and from thence adiourned to Weſtminſter the laſt day of Iuly the xv. yeare of his ſayde reigne, and there holden to the honour of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightye GOD and of holye Churche, and for the wealthe and profytte of thys hys Realme, by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the lords ſpiritual and temporall, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in thys preſente parliament aſſembled, &amp; by aucthoritye of the ſame, hath, doo, to be ordeined, made, &amp; enacted, certaine ſtatutes and ordynaunces in maner and fourme folowing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:176604:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN act concerninge brode white wollen clothes. Cap. j.</item>
               <item>An act concerninge ſtraungers artificers, for takyng of apprentices, Iourney men, and couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeruaunts. Cap. ij.</item>
               <item>An acte concernynge worſtede weauers of Yarmouth and Lynne. Cap. iij.</item>
               <item>An acte concerninge Engliſhmen veynge ſworne to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyne Prynces. Cap. iiij.</item>
               <item>¶An acte concernynge Phyſicions. Cap. v.</item>
               <item>¶An acte concerninge the high waies in the wilde of Kent. Cap. vj.</item>
               <item>¶An act for ſhoting in croſbowes and handegonnes. Cap. vij.</item>
               <item>¶An act for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixe clerkes of the Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cery to be maried. Cap. viij.</item>
               <item>¶An act co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge the liberty of Cordewayners or ſhoomakers. Ca. ix.</item>
               <item>¶An act for huntinge of the Hare. Cap. x.</item>
               <item>¶An act concerninge clothes called Veſſes made in the countye of Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke. Cap. xj.</item>
               <item>¶An acte concernynge coyners, that ſhall coyne and make money at any mint within this realme of Englande. Cap. xij.</item>
               <item>¶An act for the hauen and porte of Southampton. Cap. xiij</item>
               <item>¶An act for ſuch as be in the kinges warres ouer or vpon the ſea. Ca. xiiii.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS TABVLAE.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="acts">
            <pb facs="tcp:176604:2"/>
            <head>HENRICH OCTAVI.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>An acte concerning brode whyte wollen clothes. Cap. i.</head>
               <p>FOr as much as marchaunt ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, ſtudiyng and yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining the policies, wayes and meanes ſette aworke the people inhabited in forreine countreis and regions, with &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commodityes of this realme, and to bring the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges naturall ſubiectes from occupacion to idlenes, do day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conveigh, tranſporte and cary out of this realme of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande (for theyr owne ſingular lucre) a greate numbre of brode whyte wolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clothes, to be coloured died and wrought in diuers and ſondrie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes beyond the ſea: to the greate encreaſe comforte profit and aduauntage of the people inhabited in the ſaide outwarde and foren regions, and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter ruine decay, impoueriſſhing and vndoyng of a greate numbre of the kynges owne naturall ſubiectes. And for the effectuall furtherance of the ſayd euell ententes and purpoſes in the premiſſes the ſaid marchant ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as well by colour of enhanſyng of price of the ſayde clothes for longe dayes of payment as by fayre promiſſes and ſubtill adulacyons, haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and regrated into their handes an innumerable numbre of the ſayd clothes vpon their credence, amou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting vnto great ſummes of money farre exceding theire owne valours &amp; ſubſtance which ſommes of money many and oftentimes they haue not paied according to their appointmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, whereby the makers of the ſaid clothes, ſubtilly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed by and with their faire and flattering promiſſes, haue ſuſtayned importable loſſes, to the greate impoueryſhing of this the kynges owne realme, and to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching of the regions and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis of foreine princes.</p>
               <p>¶For remedye wherof be it enacted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinge our ſoueraigne, lord and the lordes ſpirituall and temporall and the commons in this preſent parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, and by auctoritie of the ſame, that from the feaſt of ſaynt Mighell the archangell next comming no perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons, inhabited with in this realme, of what eſtate, degree or condicion ſo euer he be of, ſhall ſell or deliuer, or cauſe to be ſolde or deliuered within this realme, by contracte couenaunt bargaine gifte or any of them or otherwyſe to any marchaunt or marchauntes ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, being borne in any of the partyes beyond y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea or els where, out of the kinges obeiſance, or to any of his or their factoures deputies, or attourneis, ſtraungers, or Englyſhmen, to the vſe of the ſayde marchant or marchantes ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers any maner of brode whyte wollen clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes, made or hereafter to be made within this realme of Englande, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peine to fortaite .xl.s. for euery clothe ſolde or deliuered after the ſayd feaſte of ſaynte Mighell, contrary to the effect and forme of this preſent acte, the one halfe of euery ſuch forfayture to be to the vſe of our ſoueraygne lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng &amp; the other halfe therof to be to the perſone or perſons other than the offender that will firſte ſue for the ſame, by originall of debte bill, playnte or informacion, in any of the kynges courtes, after the vſuall courſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:176604:3"/>
lawes and cuſtomes of the realme: In which ſute or actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the defendaunt of defendantes ſhall not be admitted to wage their law, ne any Eſſoyne, licence or protection ſhalbe alowed.</p>
               <p>¶Prouided alwaye, that if any perſon or perſons beyng the kinges natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſubiectes conueighe and bring, or cauſe to be conueighed and brought, any brode whyte wollen cloth or clothes to the common market, kept and holden in Blackwelhal within the citye of London, and do not ther cor els where bargaine vtter and ſell the ſayd cloth or clothes thither brought to or with ſome Engliſhe marchante or marchauntes within .viii. dayes, next after the ſayd cloth or clothes ſhalbe brought and ſhewed to ſell in the ſayd market: That than it ſhalbe lefull to any ſuche perſon or perſons im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the ſayde .viii. dayes, and not before, to contracte, bargaine vtter ſell and deliuer his or their ſayde cloth, or clothes, ſo brought and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, at and in the ſayd market, as is before ſayde, and bring vnſold, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and euery marchaunt ſtraunger or ſtraungers, beinge priuileged and hauing libertie to contract and bie wollen clothes freely and openly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the libertie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd citie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that the ſaid marchant or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes ſtraungers do pay and deliuer for the ſayd cloth or clothes ſo by hym or them to be bought without couin or male ingin, at and vpon the receit of the ſayd cloth or clothes, or within one moneth next enſuynge the ſayd ſale and deliuerie of the ſayd cloth or clothes, or within leſſe tyme, at the will of the ſeller therof, all ſuch hole and entier ſommes of redy money or wares, or redie mony and wares, or any of them, as was agreed &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted to be had for the ſayde clothes, by the ſayde ſellers or ſeller of them, without any other or further reſpite or dayes of paimente to be had, made or agreed, in any behalfe, any thing before contained in this preſent acte to the contrary thereof notwithſtanding</p>
               <p>¶Prouided alſo that this preſent act or any thing therin contayned bee not in any wyſe hurtful or preiudicial to any of the kinges ſubiectes for or concerning the deliuery of any ſuche wollen clothes to any marchaunt, or marchauntes ſtraungers, by reaſon of any bargaine or ſale made by them or any of them, of the ſaid clothes before the twenty day of Iulye in the .xv yere of kynge Henry the .viii. But that the ſayde kynges ſubiectes may freeely and quietly deliuer or cauſe to be deliuered the ſayd clothes, ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained and bought before the ſaid .xx. day of Iuly without any penalty or forfaiture, any thing in this preſent acte contayned to the contrary therof not withſtanding</p>
               <p>¶And be it enacted by auctority aforeſayde, that no perſon or perſons at any tyme hereafter, and before the ſayd feaſt of ſaynct Mighell, bargaine or ſell to any marchaunt or marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſtraungers-any ſuch brode white wollen clothes, to be deliuered vnto the ſayd marchaunt or marchauntes ſtraungers at any tyme after the ſame feaſt of ſaynte Mighell to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to defraud the effect &amp; trew meaning of this eſtatute, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peyne before limitted and expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176604:3"/>¶And furthermore be it prouided that euery of the kinges naturall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, at their liberties and pleaſures, may any tyme hereafter ſell and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer for redy money or wares, or for redy mony and wares, or any of them to be payed &amp; deliuered as is aforeſayd to any marchaunt or marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, al maner of brode white wollen clothes made or to be made in Coggiſhal, Bockyng, Blanctre, or any of them, and whyte clothes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Eleinforthes, and all maner of whyte brode wollen clothes with cru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilliſtes, otherwiſe called baſtardes: ſo that euery of the ſaid whyte wolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clothes, contained in this prouiſe, contein in length .xxvii. yardes at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt or aboue at the water, any thing in this preſent act contayned to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereof notwithſtanding</p>
               <p>¶And ouer this be it further prouided, ordeined and enacted by the aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aforeſayd, that it ſhallbe lefull to euery perſon or perſones, beinge the kinges naturall ſubiectes, to vtter, bargaine, contracte, ſelle and deliuer all maner of whyte brode wollen clothes to any marchaunt or marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſtraungers, in and at all common faires to be holden and kepte, within any place or places in this realme: And alſo to all and euery marchaunte ſtraunger or ſtraungers, repairing from forreine countries by the ſea, to any portes or crekes within this realme with any vittail, or other marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, at al tymes from tyme to tyme: So that all ſuch clothes, ſo or in any otherwyſe hereafter to be bargained and ſold to any marchaunte or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes ſtraungers as is before ſayd be alwaies ſold and deliuered with out couin or make ingin for redy money or wares, or for redy money, &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res or any of them, to be payed and deliuered at ſuch tyme or tymes, as is before limitted without any other or further reſpite or dayes of paymente to be had accorded and agreed in any behalfe, any thing in this preſent act conteined to the contrarie therof notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayde that no perſon or perſons, which do ſell their wollen clothe or clothes to any citizen and free man of London, without the liberty of the ſayde citye and before the ſayde cloth or clothes be conueighed and brought within the ſame citie ſhall not be compelled by any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſones to bringe their ſayde cloth or clothes ſold in fourme aboue ſaid to the market called Blackwellhal within the ſayd citee ne to pay any tolle cuſtome or other impoſicion for any libertye or eaſe to be had in the ſame Halle, for any ſuche clothe or clothes ſo ſolde but may freely at their pleaſure, bringe conueigh &amp; deliuer their ſaide clothe or clothes immediately to the houſe or houſes of ſuch citizen and free men, as did bye the ſame in fourme aforeſayde without any lette or diſturbance in any behalfe.</p>
               <p>¶And if any clothmaker, or other perſon be letted or diſturbed contrarye to this acte tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the letter or diſturber to forfait to the owner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid cloth or clothes, for euery cloth letted or diſturbed to the contrary hereof .xii.d. for which forfaiture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd owner ſhall haue his remedy againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or diſturber, by action or plainte of debt in any of the kynges courtes.
<pb facs="tcp:176604:4"/>
in which action or plaint y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defendant or defendantes ſhall not wage their lawe ne any eſſoine, licence, or protection ſhallbe allowed, this acte to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure vnto the laſt day of the next parliament.</p>
               <p>¶Prouided alwaies that this act extende not to northerne whytes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly named and called doſins, made in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Northe parties of this realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>An acte concerning ſtraungers artificers for taking of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, iourneimen, and couenant ſeruantes. C. ii</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by the kyng our ſoueraigne lord &amp; the lordes ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in this preſente parliament aſſembled, and by auctoritye of the ſame, that no maner of ſtraunger borne out of the kinges obeiſaunce be he denize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or not denizen vſing any maner of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di craft with in this realme, ſhall take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henſforthe any apren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe except the ſame apprentiſe be borne vnder the kinges obaiſaunce, vpon peine to forfait for euery apprentice, that he ſhall take contrary to this acte x.li. the one halfe therof to our ſoueraigne lorde the kinge, the other halfe to him or them that will ſue for it, be it by action of dett, byl, plainte, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion, or otherwiſe: in which ſute the defendant ſhal not be admitted to wage his law, ne any eſſoine, licence, or protection to be allowed.</p>
               <p>¶Be it alſo enacted by the auctoritie afore ſaid, and vnder lyke peine to be forfayted and recouered as is aforeſayd that no ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger being alien born, and vſing any maner of handye craft within this realme, from the feaſt of al ſainctes next enſuing, ſhal in any maner of wiſe, vſe, take. reteine or kepe into his or their ſeruiſes any maner of iourneimen or couenaunt ſeruaunt aboue the numbre of ii at one tyme, excepte the ſame iourneiman or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt ſeruaunt be borne vnder the kinges obeiſaunce</p>
               <p>And ouer this be it enacted by auctoritie aforeſaid that all maner of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bring aliens borne, vſing any maner of handye crafte, be they denizens or not denizens and inhabited within the citye of London, or ſuburbes of the ſame within the towne of weſtminſter, the pariſh of ſayncte Martins in the field, the pariſhe of our lady of the Stronde, faince Clement of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, without temple barr, ſainct Giles in the field, ſainct Andrewes in hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne, in the towne &amp; borough of Southwarke, Shordiche, whyte Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell pariſhe, ſainct Iohn ſtreete, the pariſhe of Clerkenwel ſaincte Bottol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes pariſhe without Algate, ſaincte Catherins, Barmondſay ſtreete or within two miles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of the ſaid citie of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the pariſhes aforſaid ſhalbe vnder the ſerche &amp; reformacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wardens and the felowſhippes of handy craftes within the ſayd citie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with one ſubſtancial ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger being an houſholder of the ſame craft, by the ſame wardens to be cho.ſen that is to ſay euery ſuch ſtranger, occupying any miſterie or ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di craft as is aforeſayd ſhalbe vnder the ſerch &amp; reformacion of the wardens and one ſubſtanciall ſtraunger, being an houſholder of that craft that thei ſhal ſo occupie. And that the wardens of the ſaid citie of euery ſuche handy craft
<pb facs="tcp:176604:4"/>
with one ſtraunger or houſholder as is aforeſayd of the ſame craft, haue full power and auctoritie, by this preſent act to limitte &amp; appoynt to euery ſtraunger of the miſtery &amp; handy craft that they be of, inhabitinge within the ſayde citee, ſuburbes, places or precincte, aboue remembred, a proper marke, without taking any thing therfore by the which their wares, veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and workmanſhippes that they make, may be knowne. And that the wardens of euery ſuch handy craft, and miſterye aforeſayde calling to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſtraunger of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſterie and occupacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they be of being an houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, ſhal haue full power and auctoritie, to ſerch view and refourme, as well within the ſayd citee of London. as in all other places &amp; limittes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayde all maner of wares of workmanſhippes made by any maner of ſuch handy crafte men being aliens borne, as is before ſayde.</p>
               <p>¶And that no ſtraunger borne out of the kyngs obeiſaunce vſinge any of the miſteries or occupacions of ſmithes, ioigners, or coupers ſhall make any maner of wares, or veſſelles, concerning the ſame miſteries or occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, excepte that they and euery of them put to ſuch markes to euery of the ſame wares &amp; veſſells before they ſhalbe put to ſale, or vſe as the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of their occupacions, craftes, or miſteries ſhall limitt and appoynte, without taking any thing therefore vppon peyne of forfayture the double valure of the ſame wares and veſſells: The one halfe of which forfaiture to be to the king our ſoueraigne lord the other halfe to the party that firſt will ſue for the ſame by action of dette, bille, plaint or informacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in which the defendaunr ſhal not wage his lawe, nor any eſſoyne ſhalbe caſt, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection allowed.</p>
               <p>And further it is enacted by the auctoritie aforeſaid, that if vpon any ſuch ſerche or viewe to be made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wardeins and one ſtraunger of any craft or miſterie, beforeſayd, after the fourme of this eſtatute, in veſſells or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to be found in the poſſeſſion of the workers, or owners therof putring the ſame veſſels or wares, to workemanſhip of any ſtraunger falſely and diſceitfully made, to the hurte of the kinges liege people, and ſo adiudged by the ſayd wardens and one ſtraunger: that then ſuch worker or owner, in whoſe poſſeſſion the ſame falſe and diſceitfull wares ſhalbe found, ſhall forfait the ſame wares, the one halfe therof to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king our ſoueraigne lorde and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other halfe therof to the firſt finder thereof ſuing for the ſame in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the kinges courtes by action of detinue, in which action y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defendant nor defendantes ſhal not be admitted to wage their lawe nor protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne eſſoyne be to them herein allowable.</p>
               <p>¶Be it alſo enacted by the auctoritye afore ſayde, that all wardens, and mayſters of felowſhippes of all and euery ſuch handy craftes within any ſuche citye, boroughe or towne corporate within this realme where any ſuche wardens happen to be, and in ſuche boroughes and townes corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, where no wardens of handy crafts are the bayliffes, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouernour or gouernours of the ſame boroughes or townes, ſo lacking wardens, ſhal haue lyke power and auctoritie with the bailiff or bailffes of the libertyes
<pb facs="tcp:176604:5"/>
with them where any ſuch libertye ſhalbe, being content ſo to do, to view, ſerche, and refourme ſtraungers, borne out of the kinges obeiſaunce, inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitinge and vſinge within any ſuche citye, boroughe, or towne, corporate, any maner of handy craft, in as large and ample maner as the ſayde war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and felowſhippes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid citie of London may do by vertue of this preſent acte. And that all ſtraungers vſing any of the ſayde handy craftes in any of the ſaid cities boroughes or townes, corporate, be bounden to do and obay in euery thing, according to the tenour of this preſent acte vpon lyke peines and forfaitures as is aboue remembred, to be had and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in fourme aboue reherſed.</p>
               <p>¶Prouided alwaie that if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wardens of any felowſhip or miſtery before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, bayliffes gouernour or gouernoures beforeſayd, wrongfully will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate any ſtraunger in executinge of this act, or any thinge therin contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: that than the ſtraunger ſo greeued, may by auctoritye of this acte by byll or informacion, complaine to the lorde Chauncellour and Treſorer of England, or the Iuſtices of aſſiſe in the countie for the time being, whiche by their examinacions ſhal haue ful power and auctoritie to heare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the ſame complaynt, and award to the partye compleinant ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes, as by their diſcrecions ſhal be thought reaſonable.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo that it ſhalbe lawful for and to euery the ſaid ſtraungers borne out of the kinges obeiſaunce, being a houſholder to haue and retaine aswell all and euery ſuch ſtraungers borne out of the kynges obeiſaunce. being the time of this parliament with him reteined as a iurneiman as to haue and reteine euery ſuche ſtraunger being borne out of the kinges obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunce being a prentiſe with him the tyme of this parliament this act not withſtanding. This to endure to the laſt day of the next parliament.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo that this act extend not to thinhabitauntes ſtraungers that nowe be or hereafter ſhalbe, in the vniuerſytyes of Oxforde, or Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge or within the ſainctuarie of ſainct Martins le graunde, within the ſaid citee of London.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwais, that if the ſaid wardens of the ſaid citie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with a ſtraunger, or gouernour or gouernours, of any citye or borough corporat within this realme, refuſe to make the wares of any ſtraunger, after that they be required ſo to marke that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhalbe lawful to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſtraunger or ſtraungers, to who ſuch refuſal ſhallbe made to ſel and put to ſale his ſayd wares, ſo required to be marked &amp; refuſed this act notwithſtanding. Prouided alſo, that this acte extende not to any other handicrafte, than to the craftes of ioigners, pouchmakers, coupers, and blacke ſmithes, for or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the foreſaid article of marking of wares of the ſaid eſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers. Alſo that it ſhalbe lawful to any lord of the parliamente, and euery other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges ſubiectes hauinge landes and tenementes to the yerely value of one, C, poundes, to take &amp; retaine eſtraungers ioigners and glaſiers in their ſeruice, from tyme to tyme, to and for the exerſiſyng with them their craftes, this act notwithſtanding</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:176604:5"/>
               <head>¶An acte onccrnyng worſtede weauers in Yarmouth &amp; Linne. Ca. iii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe it is diſcretely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in this preſente parliament, that the trew making &amp; draping of worſteds, ſais, &amp; ſtamins is one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt profitable occupacions of this realm: And that the ſame worſtedes, ſaies and ſtamins truely and ſubſtancial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made and wrought, bene righte acceptable and commodious marchaundiſes, as well in this realm of England, as in other foreine regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and countries, For eſtabliſhmente and good order whereof, dyuers good and lawdable eſtatutes, actes, &amp; ordinaunces, heretofore haue bene made and enacted: and namely in a parliament. holden at weſtminſter the third day of Iune, in the ſeuenth yere of the raygne of the late kinge of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory Edward the fourth. Sithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which parliamente y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makyng of the ſayd worſtedes, ſais, and ſtamins hath much encreaſed &amp; bene mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, in the citye of Norwiche, and in dyuers townes &amp; places in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of Norffolke And becauſe the townes of great Yarmouth and Linne in the ſayd countye ben townes corporated and the inhabitauntes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame townes now dayly pratiſe and vſe the making and draping of the ſayd clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes of worſtedes, ſaies and ſtamins, more buſely and diligently than they haue done in tymes paſte, to whom it is peinefull and coſtly to tranſporte and conueighe their ſaid clothes to the ſaid citie of Norwich, or to places within the ſayd county of Norffolke, which ben farre diſtaunt from ether of the ſaid townes to be ſerched and ſealed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wardens of the worſted weauers of the ſame citye of Norwick or county according to the ſayd act of parliament made the ſayd vii. yere of kinge Edwarde the fourthe. It is therfore ordeined, eſtabliſhed and enacted, by the king out ſoueraigne lord, and by the lordes ſpiritual and temporall &amp; the commons in this preſente parliament and by auctoritye of the ſame, that the craftes men called wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted weauers inhabited in the ſayde towne of greate yarmouth ſhall haue power and auctoritye by this preſent acte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth to elect and choſe yerely for euer in the munday next after the feaſte of penticoſt one honeſt man of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame miſterie and occupacion being and houſehoulder within the ſayd towne of great yarmouth &amp; hauing of his proper goodes and cattells to the value of .x.li. at the leaſt, or landes &amp; tenementes to his owne vie, of the eſtate of freehold at the leaſt to the clere yerely value of .xx.s. to be war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den of the ſame craft &amp; miſterie for the yere next enſuing, which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall perſonally appear before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayre of the ſaid citie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, for the tyme being the monday next after the feaſt of Corpus Criſti than next. enſuing, than and there to be ſworne and charged by lyke othe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the trew and ſubſtancial making of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid clothes within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid towne of great Yermouth, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foure wardens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide citie of Norwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, by vertue of the ſayd acte or parliament made in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid vii yere of king Edwarde the iiii. bene charged and ſworne for the ſame citye of Norwich And if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid maire happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be abſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid monday after Corpus Chriſti
<pb facs="tcp:176604:6"/>
or els than refuſeth to receiue or take the ſaid othe: than the ſaid warden ſo elect, within foure daies next after the ſame munday ſhall come before the bayliffes of the ſaid towne of great yarmouth for the tyme being, or before one of them, the other being abſent: &amp; than and their receiue a corporal othe for the trew exerciſing of the ſame office of wardenſhip, after the tenour of the othe accuſtomably vſed to be geuen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid wardens of the ſaid citie of Norwich. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid warde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaid towne of great Yarmouth for that tyme being, ſo electe &amp; ſworne may ordaine &amp; apoynt a ſeale with this letter .Y. to be graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſame ſeale, and maye haue full power and auctoritye to view, ſerche, ceaſe, &amp; ſeale in lead with the ſame ſeale, ſo to be appoynted &amp; engrauen &amp; none other, all worſtedes, ſaies &amp; ſtamins within the ſayd towne of yarmouth, &amp; ſuburbes of the ſame, made or to bee made &amp; not els where, in as large &amp; ample maner, as the ſayd warde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſaid citye of Norwich, &amp; wardens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid countye of Norff. or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath or haue within the ſayd citye, or countie, or in any wiſe may doe in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, by auctoritee or vertue of the before remembred act, made in the ſayd vii. yere of king Edward the fourth, any thing in the ſame act co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary notwithſtanding. ¶And that no perſon inhabited within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid towne of great yarmouth, or ſuburbes therof weaue any worſtedes ſaies or ſtamins within the ſame towne, exepte he be an Engliſh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> borne and haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apprentiſe to the ſayd occupacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and without he weaue ther ſuche proper marke as ſhalbe limitted and appoynted by the ſaide warden of the ſaid towne, for the time being, elect and ſworne, as is afore ſaid vpon peine of forfayture therof to the king our ſoueriagne lord: And that euery war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid towne ſhal limitte deſtincte and ſeuerall markes to euery of the ſaid worſtede weauers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame towne of great yarmouth, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame markes by the ſaid warden to be regeſtred in aboke.</p>
               <p>¶And alſo be it enacted by the auctoritee aforeſayd, that if and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hereafter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid towne of Linne ſhalbe inhabited with ten ſondri houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, or more number of houſhoulders, exerciſing &amp; vſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde crafte or miſterie of worſted weauers, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and from thenſforth, that is to ſaye as long as the ſame towne of Linne ſhalbe inhabited with the number of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch houſholders at the leaſt, it ſhallbe lefull to the ſame inhabitauntes of the ſayd towne of Linne yerely in the munday next after the feaſt of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt, to electe and chooſe of them ſelfe one warden of the ſayd crafte and miſterie of worſtede weauers, to be of the value in landes &amp; goodes as is beforeſaide of the warden of yarmouth: which warden ſo electe ſhall yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſworne and charged at the ſayd citye of Norwich, in lyke maner and at lyke daye, as is before limitted to the wardens of yarmouthe Or in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute of the ſayde mayre of Norwich than the ſayde warden ſo to be electe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd towne of Linne to take a corporal othe before the maire of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid towne of Lynne, within ſuche tyme, and after ſuche fourme, as is before limited vnto the warden of yarmouth. And that the ſayd warden of the ſayd towne of Linne or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme being, ſo electe and ſworne, by him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:176604:6"/>
may ordeine &amp; apoinct a ſeale, with this letter .L. to be grauen in the ſame ſeale, and may haue full power &amp; auctoritye to viewe, ſerche, ceaſe, and ſeale in lead with the ſame ſeale, ſo to be engrauen, and with none other, all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtedes, ſaies, and ſtamins, within the ſayde towne of Linne, and ſuburbes of the ſame, made or to be made, and not els where, in as large and ample maner as the ſayd warden of the Citye of Norwich, and Wardens of the ſayde county of Norff. or any of them hath or haue within the ſayd City of countye, or otherwiſe may do by auctority or vertue of the before remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred act, made in the ſayd .vij. yere of kinge Edward the fourth, any thing conteined in the ſame act to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>And that no perſon enhabited within the ſayd towne of Linne, or ſubur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes therof, make any worſtedes, ſaies, or ſtamins within the ſame towne, except he be an Engliſhman borne, and haue ben apprentiſe to the ſame oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation, &amp; without he weaue therin ſuch propre marke as ſhalbe limitted and appointed by the ſayd warden of the ſame towne of Lin, for the tyme being, vpon peine &amp; forfaiture therof to the king our ſoueraigne ne lorde: And that euery warden of the ſayd towne ſhall limit diſtinct and ſeuerall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to euerye of the worſtede weauers of the ſame towne, and the ſame markes by the ſayd warden to be regeſtred in a booke.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the auctority aforeſayd, that from the feaſt of ſainct Michaell tharchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell next comming, vnto ſuch time as the ſayd towne of Lin ſhall be inhabited with the ſayd number of ten houſholders of the ſayd craft of worſtede weauers, &amp; alwaies after, whan that number of ten houſholders ſhall happen to faile, &amp; not be inhabited in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid towne of Lin, the ſayd wardens of the ſayd city of Norwiche, &amp; their ſucceſſours, ſhal procure and cauſe one of them ſelues, or one of the wardens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde craft of the ſayde county of Norffolke, perſonnally to come &amp; be euery .xxviij day from and after the ſaide feaſt of ſainct Michaell the archangell, in and to the ſayd towne of Lyn, or within ſixe dayes next after euery ſuch .xxviii. daye, and there to continue and abide by ſo longe tyme as hee maye ſerche and ſeale all ſuch worſtedes, ſaies, and ſtamins, made in the ſame towne of Lynne, as than ſhall be broughte to hym to be ſealed, wythin the ſpace of one hole daye. And the ſayde Inhabitauntes of worſtede weauers, of the ſame towne of Lyn beynge, ſhall content and paye to the ſayd warden of Norwiche or Norff. whiche ſhall ſo come to Linne, in the ſayd .xxviij. daye or within ſixe dayes nexte after the ſayde .xxviij. day, for hys coſtes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, for euery tyme that he ſhall ſo come to Lynne, betwene the feaſtes af Saincte Michaell the archangell, and the Annunciation of our Ladye ſaincte Marye .iii s and for euerye tyme that hee ſhall ſo come to the ſayde towne of Linne betwene the feaſt of the Annunciation of our Lady, &amp; the feaſt of ſainct Michaell the archangell .ii.s. And if the ſayd inhabitauntes of worſtede weauers of the ſayd towne of Lin, do not content and pay to the ſayd warden comminge to Lyn, in forme aforeſayd, for the ſayde coſtes and charges, the ſayde .iii.s. or .ii.s. as is aboue lymytted, than the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:176604:7"/>
inhabitauntes ſhall forfaite and paye to the ſayde warden, or to his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, for euery ſuch default of payment xl.s: And if none of the ſayd war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of Norwich and Northfolke, come to the ſayd towne of Linne, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe aforeſayd, in maner and forme aboue remembred: than the ſaid war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the ſaid cittie of Norwich ſhal forfaite and pay to the ſayd inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of Linne, of the ſaid miſterie of worſtede weauers, for euery ſuch default xl.s. For recompence of which penalty and forfaites the ſayd war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of Norwich or Norff, being therunto entitled by this preſent act, by his proper name with this addicion. That is to ſay: <hi>Vnius gardianorum,</hi> or <hi>nuper vnius gardianoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> artis ſiue miſteriae textorum panni lanei vocat. VVorſtedes in ciuitate Norwich, vel comit. Norffolke,</hi> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth requyreth, ſhal and may haue action of det by writ, bill, or plaintee in any competent or lawfull court of this realme againſt the ſaide inhabitauntes of Linne, of the ſayde miſtery for the time being by theyr ſondry proper names. And the ſayde inhabitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes by theyr ſayd names, wyth this addicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Textorum pannilanei voc. VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtedes, inhabitantes ville de Linne,</hi> ſhall and maye haue like actions of dette a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſayd wardeins of Norwich, by the name of <hi>Gardiani artis ſiue mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriae textorum pannorum laneoruin voc. VVorſtedes infra ciuitatem Norway. com. Norff.</hi> To be vſed in good congruities of laten, and fourme of the lawes of this realme. In which actions, or any of them, none eſſome, protection, or wager of lawe ſhalbe ſuffered or alowed. And that the particuler bodies or goods of any of the ſayd wardeines or inhabitauntes, beinge condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in any of the ſayde actions, ſhall and maye be put in execution, after ſuche manner and forme as is vſed in actions of debt, by courſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawe of this Realme.</p>
               <p>And moreouer be it enacted by the auctority aforeſayd, that al clothes of worſtedes, ſaies, and ſtamins, made or to bee made within any of the ſayde townes of Lyn &amp; great Yarmouth, or ſuburbes of the ſame, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; marked with ſuch markes as ſhalbe limitted to the makers, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde wardens of the ſayde towne in maner and forme aboueſayd: &amp; weaued &amp; ſealed by any of the wardens of the ſayde townes of Lyn and Yarmouth in forme aboue remembred: by force and vertue of this preſent act maye be lawfully put to ſale by the owners and makers of the ſame, withoute any other marking or ſealinge vpon the ſayde clothes, or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of them to be had or made by any other wardens, dwelling or abiding without the ſayd towne, and without any arreſt, ſeiſure, or forfaiture to be had or made of or vpon any of the ſayde clothes, for lacke of any other ſeales or markes, anye thinge conteined in the ſayde former acte, made in the ſayde ſeuenth yere of kinge Edwarde the forth, to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
               <p>And ouer this be it enacted by the auctority aforeſayd, that euery crafts man of the ſaid miſtery &amp; occupation of worſtede making, dwelling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any of the ſayd townes of Lin &amp; great Yarmouth, and ſuburbes of the ſame at their owne free wylles and lyberties from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth for euer, may haue &amp; take apprentice or apprentyces (beynge male) of the age of .xiiii. yeres
<pb facs="tcp:176604:7"/>
and vpwarde, and beying the kinges naturall ſubiectes, for the terme of .vij yeres and not vnder, ſo that none of them excede the numbre of two at once to lerne, vſe, and exerciſe the ſayd crafte within either of the ſayd townes of Lyn &amp; great Yarmouth or ſuburbes of the ſame: All be it the father of the ſame apprentiſes or apprentiſe, may not expende in any landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to the yerely value of xx.s. any acte or ordinaunce to the contrary made or to be made notwithſtandinge.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway, that this preſent act nor any thinge therein conteyned, be not in any wiſe hurtefull or preiudiciall to the mayre of Norwiche, or to his ſucceſſours, or to the wardens of the ſayd Citye and county, or to their ſucceſſours, in any point article, power, or auctority, other tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for weuinge ſerching &amp; ſealinge of worſtedes, ſaies &amp; ſtamins made or to be made only within the ſayd townes of Linne &amp; Yarmouth or ſuburbes of the ſame, or to any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And for limittinge of markes to the maker of worſteds, ſaies and ſtamins, only enhabited in either of the ſayd townes or ſuburbes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of &amp; taking of appre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſes, in fourme aboue reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred: but tha y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd maire of the ſayd city of Norwiche, &amp; wardens of the ſaid city and county, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of them may haue and vſe all other poinctes, articles, power, &amp; auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torityes conteyned and ſpecified in the aboue remembred acte, made in the ſayd, vij. yere of kinge Edward the iiii. as well for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerche, ſealynge, correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reformation of the ſayd wardens newly to bee elect by vertue of this preſent acte, and euery of them, according and after ſuch forme as they may do or vſe, any of the ſayd wardeins of the ſayd city or county, by force of the ſayd acte, made in the ſayd .vii. yere of kinge Edward the fourth, as all and euery other inquiries, corrections, ſerches, ſealynges, &amp; reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be had, for the true makinge of worſtedes, ſaies, and ſtamins, in and vpon any perſon or perſons, as well within the ſayd townes of Linne and Yarmouthe as without, without trouble, lette, or vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of the ſayd townes, in as large and ample wiſe as they might haue done before the makinge of this preſent act, any thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in the ſame preſent act to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
               <p>And alſo prouyded and be it enactad, by the auctoritye aforeſayde, that the ſayd crafts men of worſtede weauers inhabited or hereafter to be inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited within either of the ſaid townes of Linne &amp; Yarmouth, or ſuburbes of the ſame, and the marchauntes or any other perſons, whiche ſhall happen to bye of the ſame craftes men or any of them, or of any other perſon, any of the ſayd clothes of worſtedes, ſtamins, or ſaies, made or to be made within either of the ſayd townes of Lin and Yarmouth, and ſealed by the ſayd wardens of the ſame towne to be elect and ſworne as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, and any of them, ſhall not ſhere, die, or put in colour, or calendre, any worſtedes, ſtamins, or ſaies, made or to be made within either of the ſayde townes of Lin &amp; Yarmouth, or ſuburbes of the ſame, in any other place or places, but onely within the ſayd city of Norwich, or ſuburbes of the ſame vpon peine of forfaiture of euery peece of worſtede, ſaies, or ſtamins to be
<pb facs="tcp:176604:8"/>
made wythin any of the ſaid townes of Lyn and Yarmouth, or ſuburbs of the ſame, or the value therof, ſhorne, died, coloured, or calendred by enye of the ſayde craftes men, biers, or marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in any other place or places than in the ſayd city of Norwich or ſuburbs of the ſame: the one half ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be to the kinge our ſoueraigne lorde, and the other half therof to ſuch perſon or perſons as ſhal ceaſe the ſame: ſo that the ſaide worſteds brought to the ſayd city of Norwich to be ſhorne, died, coloured, &amp; calendred, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out couin or craft of any of the ſayd inhabitauntes &amp; marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, may be ſhorne, died, coloured, and calendred at and by as conuenient price or prices and in as redy wiſe as the ſayd inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of either of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd towns of Lyn and Yarmouth, &amp; marchantes biers of the ſayd worſtedes, or other of the ſayd citye or county hath had in times paſt, or hereafter ſhall haue.</p>
               <p>And alſo that the inhabitauntes and marchauntes &amp; euery of them, ſo bringinge their ſayd worſtedes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame city for to be ſhorne, died, colored &amp; cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, be reaſonably &amp; lawfully entreated according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid act made in the ſayd .vij. yere of kinge Edward the fourth, &amp; the ordinances made &amp; affirmed, or hereafter to be made &amp; affirmed for the ſayd miſtery, without let or diſturbaunce, contrary to the ſame acte or ordinance in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>And be it enacted by the auctority aforeſayd, that no perſon or perſons any time after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey or tranſport into any of the parties of beyond the ſea any maner of clothes of worſtedes before the ſame clothes be ſhorne, died, colored, &amp; calendred, vpon peine of forfaiture the value therof: the one half to the king our ſoueraigne lord, &amp; tho ther half therof to the party that will ſue therfore, by action or plaint of debt in any of the kynges courtes: In whiche action or ſuite no protection or eſſoyne ſhalbe alowed, nor the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der admitted to wage his lawe. This act to endure to the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An Act concerninge Engliſhmen beyng ſworne to forren princes. Cap. iiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Raien the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that where ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and diuers perſons being the kinges ſubiectes naturally borne within this his realme, haue wdrawen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues out of the ſame realme, and tranſported them ſelues with theyr wiues, children and goods, into Hollande, zeland, Barband Flaunders, and into other countries of forren princes, and there be ſworn to the obeiſaunce of the princes, and lordes of the countreis, where they be now inhabited, makynge their great buildinges, and be contributories to all maner of charges, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubiectes of thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis be: &amp; thus they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine aſmuch as in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, the cities, boroughes, &amp; townes of thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis and many mo of the kinges ſubiects intend to do the ſame, if remedy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be not prouided: Which ſubiects borne in England, notwithſtandinge, that they this eſtraunge theym ſelues from the kynges obeyſaunce, yet they occupy here in all the portes, hauens, and crekes, cities, boroughes, &amp; townes of England, as frely and as free in cuſtome and ſubſidy as the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſubiectes do occupy, and not onely for them ſelfe, but alſo colourably
<pb facs="tcp:176604:8"/>
for other ſtraungers, their frendes, &amp; partiners, and alſo make them ſelues quite and exempte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all charges within this realme, in preiudice &amp; decay of the cities, townes &amp; boroughes of England: and as for beyonde the ſea they will obey to none auctority grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſh nation, by the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges highnes and his noble progenitours, vnder the great ſeale of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and by auctority of parliamente, but they giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ouer to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; defence of thoſe outwarde princes, to whom they be ſworn ſubiects And by theſe maner of perſons much coyne is conueyed out of the Lande. Wherefore be it ordeyned and enacted, by the kinge our ſoueraygne lorde &amp; the lordes ſpirituall &amp; temporall, &amp; the commons in this preſente parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled &amp; by the auctority of the ſame, that all and euery ſuche ſubiectes borne in England, and ſworne to be ſubiectes to forren princes &amp; lordes of outwarde parties, from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth (as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as they ſhall ſo abide, &amp; be as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes to forren prynces &amp; lordes) that from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth ſo longe they &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riche of them ſhall pay ſuch cuſtomes, ſubſidy, tolle, and other impoſicions within this realme of Englade. as other ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers of thoſe partes wher the ſayd Engliſhemen make their inhabitacion: pay or vſe to paye wythin this ſayd realme: And that the knowledge of all and euery ſuche perſon or perſons inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and ſworne in maner and forme as is before reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within the Archedukes countries, that is to ſay, Holand, Zeland, Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande &amp; Flaunders onely, ſhalbe had by certificat thereof made by the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the marchaunt auenturers, and the aſſiſtens there for the time being: and alſo for all other reamels and countrees of forren prynces to be certified by the kinges moſte noble imbaſidours, beinge at ſuch tyme there as they ſhall happen to be in the ſayd countries vpon the kinges affayres, ſhall likewyſe certifie, as is beforeſayd vnder their ſeale into the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cery of our ſoueraigne lorde the king: and thereupon oute of the ſayde chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cery writtes to be made &amp; directed vnto the cuſtomers, controllers, or other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the kynges cuſtome, in euery port, hauen, or creke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in thys ſayde realme, to perceiue, leuy, &amp; take all maner of ſuch cuſtomes, ſubſydies, tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, &amp; other impoſitions, as is before ſpecified, of all ſuche goods and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundiſes, as ſhall belong vnto any ſuch perſon or perſons inhabited and ſworne, in maner and fourme aboue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as well inward as outward.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway, that if hereafter it ſhall happen any ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to retourne into the realme, &amp; here to tary and inhabite: that than he or they ſhalbe reſtored to all ſuch liberties and fredoms in paying of cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes or ſubſidies and other charges, as all other Engliſhemen dothe vſe to pay, and to haue a wryt out of the chauncery for the ſame, this acte or any thinge therin made, to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte concerninge Phyſicions. Cap. v.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>n their moſt humble wiſe ſheweth vnto your highnes, your true &amp; faithfull ſubiects &amp; liege men, Iohn Chambre, Thomas Linacre Fernandus de Victoria, your phiſicions, and Nicholas Halſewell,
<pb facs="tcp:176604:9"/>
Iohn Fraunces, and Robert yaxley, and all other men of the ſame faculty within the city of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, and .vij miles about, that where your highnes (by your moſt gracious letters patentes, bearinge date at weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. the .xxiij day of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre the .x. yere of your moſt noble reign) for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth of this your realme, in due exerciſinge and practiſinge of the faculty of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke and the good miniſtracion of medicins to be had, haue incorporat and made of vs and of our company aforeſayd, one body and perpetuall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty or felowſhip of the faculty of Phiſicke, and to haue perpetuall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſeale, and to choſe yerely a preſident of the ſame felowſhip &amp; comminalty to ouerſe rule, and gouerne the ſayd felowſhip and commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, and all men of the ſame faculty, with diuers other liberties and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges, by your highnes to vs graunted, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth of this your realme, as in your ſayde moſte gracious letters patentes more at large is ſpecified and conteined, the tenour whereof foloweth in theſe woordes.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ENRICVS dei gratia, rex Angliae, &amp; Francie, &amp; dominus Hiberniae, Omnibus, ad quos praeſentes litterae pondenerint, Salutem. Cum regii officii noſtri munus arbitremur ditionis noſtre hominum foelicitati omni ratione conſulere: Id autem vel in primis fore, ſi improborum coratibus tempeſtiùe occurramus, apprime neceſſarium duximns. improbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qua<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> hominum, qut medicinam magis auaritae ſuae cauſa quam vllius bone conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae fiducia profitebuntur, vnde rude &amp; credule plebu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>lurima incommoda oriantur, audaciam compeſcere. Ita<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> partim bene inſtitutarum ciuitatum in Italia, &amp; aliis multis nationibus exemplum imitati, partim grauium virorum ductorum Ioannis Chambye, Thomae Linacre, Fernandi de Victoria medicorum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum, Nicholai Halſwell, Ioannis Franciſcei, &amp; Roberti Yaxley, medîcorum, ac precipue reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſsimi in Chriſto patris, ac domini, domini Thomae Tituli ſauctae Ceciliae, trans Tiberim ſacroſanctae Romanae excleſiae preſbiteri cardinalis Eboracenſis Archiepiſcopi, &amp; regni noſtri Angliae cancellarii chariſſimi precibus inclinati, collegium perpetuum doctorum &amp; grauium virorum, qui medicina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vibe noſtra Londino &amp; ſuburbibus intra<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ſeptem millia paſſuum, abea vrbe quaqua verſus publice exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant, inſtitui volumus at<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> imperamus, Quibus tum ſui honoris tum publice vtilitatis nomine cure, vt ſperaenius crit, malicioſorum, quorum meminimus inſcritam temeritatem<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan>, tam exemplo grauitaté<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ſuà deterrere quàm per leges miſtras nuper editas, ac per conſtitutiones per idem collegium condendas punire. Quae quo facilius rite peragi paſsint memoratis doctoribus Ioanni Chambre, Thomae Lincare, Fernan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do de Victoria medicis noſtris. Nicholai Halſewell, Ioanni Franciſco, &amp; Roberto Yaxley, medicis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſſimus, quod ipſi om<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>éſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> homines eiuſdem facultatis de &amp; in ciuitate pradicta, ſint in re &amp; nomine vnum corpus &amp; communitas perpetua, ſiue collegium perpetuum Et ꝙ eadem communitas ſiue colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium ſingulis annis in perpetuum eligere poſſint &amp; facere de communitate illa aliquem prouidum virum &amp; in facultate medicinea expertum in praeſidentem etuſdem collegii ſiue communitatis, ad ſuperuiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, recognoſcendum, &amp; gubernandum pro illo anno collegium, ſiue commumitatem praedict. &amp; omnes homines eiuſdem facultatis &amp;, regotia eorudem, Et ꝙ preaſidens &amp; collegium ſiue communitas habeant ſucceſſionem perpetuam, &amp; commune ſigillum negotii dict. communitatis &amp; praeſidentis in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum ſeruiturum Et ꝙ ipſi &amp; ſucceſſores ſui in perpetuum ſint perſone habiles &amp; capaces ad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirendum &amp; poſſidendum in feodio &amp; perpetuitate terras &amp; tenementa, redditus &amp; alias poſſeſsiones quaſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>u<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan>
                           </p>
                           <p>¶Conceſsimus etiam eis &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis pro nobis &amp; haeredibus noſtris quód ipſi &amp; ſucceſſores ſu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> poſsint perquirere ſibi &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis, ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dicta vrbe quam exrta terras &amp; tenta quaecun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> annuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> valorem duodecim librar. non exceden, ſtatuto de alienatione ad manum mortuam non obſtante. Et ꝙ
<pb facs="tcp:176604:9"/>
ipſi per nomina praeſidentis collegii, ſeu communitatis facultatis medicine, Lond, plitati &amp; impritati poſſint coram quibaſcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> iudicibus in curiis &amp; actionibus quibuſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que. Et ꝙ praedict. praeſidens &amp; col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium ſiue communitas, &amp; eorum ſucceſſores congregationes licitas &amp; honeſtas de ſe ipſis ac ſtatutae &amp; ordinationes, pro ſalubri gubernatione ſuperuiſu &amp; correctione collegii, ſeu communitatis praedictae, &amp; omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominum eandë facultate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dictae ciuitate ſeu per ſeptem miliaria in circuitu eiuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ciuitatis exercen. ſecundum neceſſitatis exigentiam (quoties &amp; quando opus fuerit) facere valeant licite &amp; impune, ſine impedimento noſtri, haeredum vel ſucceſſorum noſtro riuſticiarioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſcaetorum, vice comitum, &amp; aliorum balliuorum, vel miniſtrorum noſtrorum haeridum vel ſucceſſorum noſtrorum quorumcunque. Conceſſimus etiam eiſdem praeſidenti &amp; collegio, ſeu communitati &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis ꝙ nemo in dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ciuitate, aut per ſeptem miliaria in circuitu eiuſdem, exerceat dictam facultatem, niſi ad hoc per dictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praeſidentem &amp; communitatem, ſeu ſucceſſores eorum, qui pro tempore fuerint, admiſſus ſit per eiuſdem praeſidentis &amp; Collegii litteras ſigillo ſuo communi ſig illatas, ſub poena tentum ſolidorum pro quolibet menſe, quo non admiſſus eandem facultatem exercuit, dimidium inde nobis &amp; haeredibus noſtris. &amp; dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium dicto praeſidenti &amp; collegio applicandum.</p>
                           <p>¶Praeterea volumus &amp; concedimus pro nobis &amp; ſucceſſoribus noſtris (quantum in nobis eſt) ꝙ per praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem &amp; collegiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praedictae communitatis pro tempore exiſten. &amp; corum ſucceſſores imperpetuum qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor ſingulis annis per ipſos eligantur, qui habeat ſuperuiſum &amp; ſcrutinium correctionem &amp; gubernati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, omnium, &amp; ſingulorum dictae ciuitatis medicorum vtentium facultate medicinae in cademciuitate, ac a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>liorum medicorum forinſecoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quorumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> facultatem illam medicine aliquo modo frequentatium &amp; vtentium infra eandem ciuitatem &amp; ſuburbia eiuſdem, fiue intra ſeptem miliaria in circuitu eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ciuitatis, ac punitione eorundem pro delictis ſuis in non bene exequendo faciendo &amp; vtendo illa. Nec non ſuperuiſum &amp; ſcrutinium omni modo medicinarum &amp; eorum reception, per dict<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s medico<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, ſeu aliquem eorum huiuſmodi ſig eis noſtris pro eorum infirmitatibus eurandis &amp; ſanandis dandis imponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, &amp; vtendis, quotiens &amp; qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do opus fuerit pro commodo &amp; vtilitate eorundem ligeoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtrorum. Itae ꝙ punitio huiuſmodi medicorum vtentium dicta facultate medicine, ſic in praemiſſis delinquentium per fines, amerciamenta, &amp; inpriſonamenta corporum ſuorum, &amp; per alias vias rationabiles, &amp; congruas exequatur.</p>
                           <p>¶Volumus etiam &amp; concedimus pro nobis haeredibus &amp; ſucceſſoribus noſtris (quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in nobis eſt) ꝙ nec praeſidens, nec aliquis de collegio praedicto medicorum, nec ſucceſſores ſui, nec eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliquis exercens fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatem illam, quoquo modo in futur. infra ciuitatem noſtram praedictam, &amp; ſuburbia eiuſdem, ſeu alibi ſummoneantur, aut ponantur, ne<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> eorum aliquis ſommmoneatur, aut ponatur in aliquibus aſſiſis, iuratis, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtis, inquiſitionibus, attinctis, &amp; altis recognitionibus infra dictam ciuitatë, &amp; ſuburbia eiuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterum coram maiore ac vicicom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeu coronatoribus dictae ciuitatis noſtrae pro tempore exiſten. capien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, aut per alique<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> officiarium, ſeu miniſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuum, vel officiarios ſiue miniſtros ſuos ſummonend. licet iide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iurati, inquiſitiones ſeu recognitiones ſommon fuerint ſuper breui, vel breuibus noſtris, vel haeredum noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trorum de recto, ſed ꝙ dicti magiſtri, ſiue gubernatores, ac communitas facultatis antedicte &amp; ſucceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſui et eorum quilibet dictam facultatem exercentes, verſus nos, haeredes, et ſucceſſores noſtros, ac ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus maiore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vic<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>comites ciuitatis noſtrae praedictepro te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore exiſtente) et quoſcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> officiarios, et miniſtros ſuos ſint inde quieti, et penitus exonerati imperpetuum per praeſentes.</p>
                           <p>¶Prouiſo quod litterae noſtrae, ſeu aliquid in eïs content, non cedent in praeiudicium ciuitatis noſtrae Lond. ſeu libert eiuſdem. Et hoc abſque fine ſeu feodo pro praemiſſis, ſeu ſigillatione praeſentium nobis facienda, ſoluenda, vel aliqualiter, reddenda, aliquo ſtatuto, ordinatione, vel actu in contrarium ante haec tempora facto, edito, ordinato ſeu prouiſo in aliquo non obſtante In cuius rei teſtimonium has litteras fieri fecimus patentes. Teſte me ipſo apud weſtmonaſterium .xxiii. die Septembr. Anno regni noſtri decim. Per ipſum re<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> gem et de datae praedictae auctoritate Parliamenti.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Tunſtall.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176604:10"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd for ſo much that the makyng of the ſayd corporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is meritorious &amp; very good for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth of this your realme, it is therefore expedient and neceſſary to prouide, that no perſon of the ſayde politike body and comminalty aforeſayde, be ſuffered to exerciſe and practiſe Phiſike, but only thoſe perſons that be profounde, ſad, &amp; diſcret, grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned and deepely ſtudied in Phiſicke.</p>
               <p>In conſideration wherof, and for the further auctoriſinge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes, and alſo enlargeyng of further articles for the ſayd common wealth to be had &amp; made: Pleaſeth it your highnes with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſente of your lords ſpirituall and temporal and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, to enacte, ordaine and eſtabliſh that the ſayde corporacion of the ſayd comminaltie and felowſhip of the faculty of Phiſike afore ſayde, and all and euery graunte, article and other thinge contained, and ſpecified, in the ſaid letters patentes, be approued, graunted, ratified, and confirmed in this preſent parliamente, and clerly auctoryſed and admytted by the ſame good, lawfull, and auailable, to your ſayde bodye corporat, and theyr ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours for euer in as ample and large maner as maye be taken, thought, conſtrued by the ſame. And that it pleaſe your highnes with the aſſent of your ſayd lordes ſpirituall and temporall and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in thys your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament, aſſembled, furtherly to enacte, ordeyne, and ſtabliſhe, that the ſixe perſons beforeſayd, in your ſaid moſt gracious letters patentes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as principalles, and firſt named of the ſayde comminaltye and felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe, choſinge to them twoo moe of the ſayde comminaltye from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forwarde, be called and cleaped electes. And that the ſame Electes yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſe one of them to be preſident of the ſayd comminalty, and as ofte as any of the roumes and places of the ſame Electes ſhal fortune to be voyde by death or otherwyſe, than the ſuperuyſours of the ſame Electes (within xxx. or xl. dayes nexte after the death of theym or anye of theym) ſhall choſe, name, and admitte one or moe, as neede ſhall require, of the moſt conning, and experte men, of and in the ſayde faculty in London, to ſupply the ſaide roume and numbre of eight perſons. So that he or they that ſhalbe ſo cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, be firſt by the ſayd ſuperuiſors ſtraitly examined, after a forme deuiſed by the ſayde Electes, &amp; alſo by the ſame ſuperuiſours approued. And where that in diociſes of England out of London it is not light to finde alwaye men able ſufficiently to examine (after the ſtatute) ſuche as ſhalbe admyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to exerciſe Phiſike in them: that it may be enacted in thys preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that no perſon from henceforth he ſuffred to exerciſe or practyſe in Phiſicke through Englande, vntill ſuch tyme that he be examined at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by the ſayd preſident and three of the ſayd Electes and to haue from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid preſident or Electes letters teſtimonials of their approuynge and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, except he be a graduate of Oxforde or ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bridge, whiche hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed all thynges for his forme without any grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:176604:10"/>
               <head>An act concerning the high wayes in the wilde of Kent. Ca. xi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N humble wiſe beſecheth your highnes your true and faithfull ſubiecte George Gilford ſquier for your body, that where there is and of tyme whereof mynd of man is not to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary hath bene an olde common waye or ſtreete for cariers, and all other paſſages and buſineſſe for you and your progenitoures and you and their people in the hundred of Cranebroke, in the wilde of your county of Kente, leading and extending betwene and amonge the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of hempſtede of the ſayd George in the ſayde hundrede of Cranbroke, fro the bridge called hempſtede bridge diuiding the ſayd hundred of Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke and the hundred of Roluinden in the ſame weld of your ſayd county to a croſſe called Contenden croſſe ſtandinge nighe to a greate Oke, named Hempſtede oke which is in length vpon a hundred foure ſcore and ten per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: which common way ſo vſed is in diuers places thereof ryght deepe annoyous for the paſſage of your people, and alſo is not ſo directely leading betwene the ſayd bridge and croſſe neither ſo cominodious for your people as an other way of lyke bredth in other places within and ouer the landes of the ſayd maner mought be made.</p>
               <p>In conſideracion wherof, in maye pleaſe your highneſſe of your bleſſed diſpoſicion with the aſſente of the lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons in this preſente parliamente aſſembled and by the auctoritye of the ſame to enacte ordayne that it ſhalbe lefull to your ſayde beſecher his heires and aſſignes, owners of the ſayde maner of Hempſtede, at his and their propre coſtes &amp; charges at any time on this ſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxvii. day of May which ſhallbe in the yere of our lord god .M.D.xxvii. by the ouerſighte and aſſent of two Iuſtices of peace of the ſaid county of Kente and .xii other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrete men, inhabitauntes within the ſayde hundredes of, Cranbroke &amp; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiden, to aſſigne, limitte and laye ouer and thoughe the landes of the ſayde manour one other way, for cariages &amp; paſſages of your grace and of your people and your and their heires and ſucceſſoures, of as great large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in bredeth or larger than the ſayd olde waye now being is, and as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modious for the ſayd cariages and paſſages, as the ſame waye now being is or better extending and leading dyrectly betwene the ſayde bridge and croſſe, ſo that your grace and your people by the ſayd new way ſo to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned and layed out, ſhall haue the more eaſye cariage, and paſſage, than is or of late tyme hath bene by the ſayd olde waye. And that after the ſayde new way ſo layde out and aſſigned the ſayde cariages, paſſages and other buſineſſe there may be as liberally, commonly, and freely from thens forthe there vſed and had for euer, and euery other thinge there exerciſed &amp; kept, as before this tyme hath bene had and vſed, exerciſed and kept in the ſayd olde waye with out let or interrupcion of the ſayd George his heyres or his aſſignes, or any other perſonne which hereafter ſhall haue. holde, or poſſede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid manet. And that immediately after that the ſayde new way
<pb facs="tcp:176604:11"/>
(as is beforeſayd) to be aſſigned and limitted ſhalbe as is aboueſayd layed out and fully made, it ſhall be lefull to your ſayde beſecher, his heires, and aſſignes owners of the ſaid manour to encloſe the ſaid old way and eueri party therof: And that fro hensforth to holde in ſeueralty to them, and to their heires and aſſignes to their owne vſe and profit for euer as parcel of the ſaid manour, without any commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> way or paſſage their fro thensforth to be had or claimed any preſcripcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vſe to the contrarye heretofore had not withſtanding.</p>
               <p>¶And in conſideracion that many other commom waies in the ſaid weld of Kent be ſo depe and noyous by wearing and courſe of water and other occaſions that people can not haue their cariages or paſſagss by horſes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon or by the ſame: But to their great peines, petil, and ieoperdye: it may be by the ſayd auctoritie enacted and eſtabliſhed, that if any other perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons any tyme hereafter in any place within the ſayd weld of your ſaid countye, of his good mynd and diſpoſicion, without any value of good by him or them to be receiued for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, will for the common weale of your people aſſigne and lay out a more commodious way in and ouer the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des thervnto adioyninge wherof the perſon or other to his vſe ſhalbe ceaſed of fee in eſtate of inheritaunce that the ſame new way ſo to be aſſigned and layd out, by ouerſight and aſſent of two Iuſtices of peace of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, and .xii. other diſecrete me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inhabitinge within hundred, where any ſuche new way ſhalbe limitted &amp; layde out, or inhabiting within the ſame hundred and other hundreds to that hundred nexte adioyninge ſhallbe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thensforth, holden, occupied, and vſed in lyke maner as the olde waye ther now is or before hath bene</p>
               <p>¶And that alſo the ſame perſon or perſons, ſo diſpoſed, willynge, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhynge the ſame, ſhall and may for the ſaide new waye ſo aſſygned and vſed, retaine and holde in way of recompence for the ſame new way ſo to be geuen, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoyle and grounde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde way in ſeueralty as is aboue ſayd, to him or them and to their heires for euer. in lyke maner as is aboue ſayd of the ſayd new waye to be aſſigned at Hempſtede. And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde two Iuſtices of peace, &amp; .xii other diſcrete perſons by whoſe ouerſight and aſſent, the ſayde new waye at Hempſtede, or any other waye by vertue of this acte ſhallbe hereafter aſſigned, limitted and layde out, ſhal within thre monethes next after the aſſignement limittacion, &amp; laying out of the ſame make certificate into the kinges moſt honorable courte of Chauncery vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſeales, of the length and bredeth of the ſame new way or ſtrete &amp; of other thinges adioyning or concerning the ſame as by their diſcrecions ſhalbe thought moſt expedient or requiſite for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre to be certified: And that certificat to be made fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time as often as any ſuche new waye or ſtrete ſhalbe aſſigned, limitted, and laied out in forme aboue written.</p>
               <p>¶Prouided alway that if any perſon, or perſons, or bodye politike, haue or ought to haue, or hereafter ſhall haue any churche way or other what ſo
<pb facs="tcp:176604:11"/>
euer way or paſſage, ouer or through any maner landes adioyning to any of the ſayd olde wayes or ſtretes, which ſhallbe taken, and vſed by force ol this acte, as ſeuerall ſoyle and free holde in recompence for any new waye to be made &amp; layed out, in fourme aforeſaid, or haue or ought to haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall haue landes or tenementes adioyning to the ſayd olde way that they and euery of them, their heires, and ſucceſſours, ſhall and maye haue and vſe their ſayd waye or wayes, out of and into the ſayd new way ouer and through the land of the ſayd olde waye, or ſtreete, into or ouer the ſayd lande or tenement adioyning to the ſame, &amp; ſo to paſſe and repaſſe as ſhal appertaine ouer the ſame olde waye at ſuch conuenient place or places thereof, as therefore ſhalbe limitted and aſſigned by the ſayd two Iuſtices of peace and other .xii. men, and by them to be certifyed into the chauncerie among other thinges by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be certified in fourme aforeſaide: any thing in this acce aboue written notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>An acte concerning ſhoting in croſbowes and hand gonnes. Cap. vii</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by the kinge our ſoueraige lord, by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his lordes ſpiritual and temporall and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliament aſſembled &amp; by aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the ſame, that euery perſon and perſons hauing landes, tenementes, hereditamentes, fees, anuities, or other yerely profites in his owne right or in his wiues to the yerely value of one hundred poundes, from henſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forth may lawfully vſe and ſhote in croſbowes and hand gonnes, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of them, &amp; retayne and kepe the ſame: Any thing contained in the acte made at a parliament holden at weſtminſter, in the ſixt yere of the raygne of our ſoueraigne lord, for reformacion of ſhotyng in croſbowes and hand gonnes, and for keping of the ſame notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>And further be it enacted by auctoritie aforeſaid that al licences graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and placardes made by our ſayde ſoueraigne lord to any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, before the .xx. day of Auguſt in the .xv. yere of his raigne for ſhowting in croſbowes or hand gonnes, or for kepynge of the ſame, or any of them, ſhalbe from the feaſt of ſainct Michael the archangel next comming vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voyd and of none effecte.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted, by the auctoritie aforeſayde that euery perſon, not hauing in vſe or poſſeſſion, landes, teu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, fees, annutties, or other yere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly profites, to the yerely value of .C. poundes (as aforeſayde) offending con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſayd acte, made in the ſayd .vi. yere, ſhall forfaite for euery tyme that he ſhal ſo offende, but onely .xl.s. and the croſbowes &amp; hand gonnes to he had. recouered, ſeaſed, &amp; leuied according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd former act any thing contained in the ſayd former acte of or for any greater penalti notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding. And that it ſhalbe leful to all Iuſtices of peace in their ſeſſions and ſtewardes &amp; bailiffes, in their leetes, to enquire of euery perſon, &amp; perſones
<pb facs="tcp:176604:12"/>
other than be prouided for by this preſent acte, offending contrary to the ſaid form<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t acte, of or for any great penalty notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>¶And that it ſhallbe lefull to all iuſtices of peace in their ſeſſions, and ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes and bailiffes in their leetes to enquire of euery perſon &amp; perſons other than be prouided for by this preſent acre, offendinge contrary to the ſayd former act: &amp; that vpon all preſentmentes had before iuſtices of peace in their ſeſſions, proceſſes ſhalbe made for leuiynge of the ſayde .xl.s. to the kinges vſe, in ſuch fourme and in lyke maner as is made vpon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enditeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of riottes, and vpon euery preſentmente had in any leetes the lorde and owners of the leetes to leuie and haue the ſayd penalty if .xl.s by way of diſtreſſe, accion of dette, or otherwiſe in the which the offender ſhal not be admitted to wage his law, ne any eſſoyne or protection to be alowed.</p>
               <p>¶And be it further enacted by auctoritye afore ſayde, that no lordes or owners of leetes beare or mayntaine any of their tenauntes or ſeruauntes within the iuriſdiction of their leetes to do or offend contrary to the ſayd former act, vpon peine to forfane for euery time ſo doing .xl.s. the one halfe therof to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king our ſoueraigne lorde, and the other halfe to the parti that wil ſue for the ſame by action of dette, byl plaint or informacion in which ſute no wager of law ne eſſoyne or protection ſhalbe alowed or admitted. The olde act in al other poyntes, not otherwiſe prouided for in this acte, to be of force and effecte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An act concerning the ſix clerkes of the Chauntery to be maried. Cap. viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N moſt humble wiſe beſecheth your trew &amp; faithful ſubiectes &amp; dayly ſeruauntes the ſixe clerkes of your high courte of Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerie, that wheras of olde tyme accuſtomed hath bene vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid court y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al maner clerkes and miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame courte wryting to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ſeaſe, ſhold be vnmaried except onlye the clerke of the crowne: ſo that as wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſetoures &amp; other clerkes, as the ſixe clerkes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Chauncerie wear by the ſame cuſtome eſtrained from mariage, wherby all thoſe that contrarye to the ſame dyd mary, were no longer ſuffered to write in the ſaid Chauncery not onely to their great hinderance, loſing therby the benefite of their longe ſtudie and tedious laboures and peines in youthe, takine in the ſayd court, by alſo to the great decaye of the trew courſe of the ſayd court.</p>
               <p>¶And for as muche as the ſayde cuſtome taketh no place nor vſage, but onely in the office of the ſayde ſixe clerkes but that it is permitted and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for maintenance of the ſayd courte, that as wel the ſaid courſetoures as the other clerkes aforeſaid, may and doe take wiues and mary at their lybertye after the lawes of holy churche, and of longe tyme haue ſo done, without interruption or left of any perſon: It may therefore pleaſe your highneſſ of your moſt aboundant grace, with the aſſent of the lordes ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="tcp:176604:12"/>
and temporall and the commons in this preſent parlyamente aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by auctoritye of the ſame, in conſideration of the premiſſes, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd alſo for that the ſayd cuſtome is not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon any law, to ordeine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acte, and eſtabliſhe, that Iohn Treuerthen, Rycharde Welles, Oliuer <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Iohan Croke, Wyllyam Ieſſen, and Iohn Lemſey, nowe beynge in the office of the ſixe clerkes of the Chauncery, &amp; euery of them, and all other whiche in time to come ſhalbe in the ſame office, &amp; euery of them, may and do take wiues &amp; mary at their liberty, after the laws of holy churche.</p>
               <p>And that they and euery of them ſo maryed maye haue, holde, and enioyne, their ſayd office of ſixe clerkes in as ample, large, and like manner, as they did or ſhould do before the ſayd eſpouſelles, or as if they had neuer ben ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, the ſayd cuſtome or any other cuſtome or ordinaunce heretofore had or made to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwaye, that by any thinge in this acte conteined the maiſter of the Rolles (for the time being) be not preiudiced either in the geuing and diſpoſicion of the ſayde offices from time to time, as hath beene heretofore accuſtomed, the forfaiture of that office by reaſon of mariage onely excepte. And that the ſayd officers, which nowe be &amp; hereafter ſhalbe, do geue ſuch attendance vnto the ſayd maiſter of the Rolles for the tune being, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in the ſayd offices hath bene accuſtomed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An act co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge the liberty of Cordwainers or ſhowmakers. Cap. ix.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Raien the commons in this preſente parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that where in the parliament holden at Weſtmin. in the fourth yere of the reigne of the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prince of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory Edward the .iiij. late kinge of Englande your noble graunfather, among other things it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined, eſtabliſhed, and enacted, that no perſon cordwai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the city of London, or within three myles next a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame, vpon any ſonday of the yeare, in the feaſtes of the Natiuity or Aſcencion of our lord, or Corpus Chriſti, ſhould ſell, commaund or make to be ſolde any ſhowes, bootes, or galeges, or vpon any of the ſayd ſondaies or feaſtes, ſhould put vpon the foote or legges of any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s any ſhowes, boot<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, or galeges, vpon peine to forfaite and loſe twenty ſhillyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſterlitge, as often and whanſoeuer any perſon ſhoule doe contrary to the ſayd ordinaunce, or any parcell thereof.</p>
               <p>And where by the ſame eſtatute it is ordeyned and prouyded, that the ſame acte ſhould not extende to the domage or preiudice, nor any manner be hurtefull or preiudiciall to the Deane and Chapiter (for the time beinge) of the free chapell of the kynge, of Sainct Martins le graunde of London nor to any perſon or perſons, Dwellinge, Abidinge, or Beinge within any place or places in ſainct Martyns lane in London, or wythin any place or places within the precincte, fee, or fraunchyſe, of the ſayde Deane, or of the
<pb facs="tcp:176604:13"/>
ſayde Deane and chapiter. Wherefore to the honour of almighty god and to the intent that the kinges ſubiectes may be hereafter at their liberty, as well as the ſayd inhabitauntes within the liberties and precinct of the ſaid ſainct Martines the graund, be it enacted by the auctority of this preſente parliament, that the ſayd eſtatute, made in the parliament holden at weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter in the ſayd fourth yere of the reigne of kinge Edwarde the fourth, ſtande and be from henceforth vtterly voyde and of none effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An act concenigne the huntinge of the Hare. Cap. x.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as muche as our ſoueraygne lorde the kynge, and other noble men of thys realme of Englande, before this time hathe vſed and exerciſed the game of huntynge of the Hare, for their dyſporte and pleaſure, whyche game is nowe decayed and almooſte vtterly dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied, for that, that diuers perſons in dyuers partyes of thys Realme, by reaſon of the traſinge in ſnow, haue killed and deſtroied, and dayly do kill and dyſtroy the ſame Hares, by .x.xij. or .xvj. vpon a daye, to the dyſpleaſure of our ſaid ſoueraigne lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinge &amp; to other noble men of this his realme Wherefore be it enacted by our ſayd ſoueraigne lorde, by the lordes ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and temporall, and the commons in thys preſente Parlyamente aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by auctoritye of the ſame: that no perſon or perſonnes of what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate degree, or condicion they be, from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth trace, diſtroye, and kill no Hare in ſnow with any dogge, bytche, nor otherwyſe. And that the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the peace within euery ſhire, at euery ſeſſions of the peace, and ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes of leetes ſhall haue full auctority anb power to power to enquyre of ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. And after ſuch inquiſitions found, the ſayd Iuſtices of the peace &amp; ſtewardes of leetes for euery Hare ſo killed, ſhall ſeaſſe vpon euery ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender .vi.s.viij.d. to be forfaited to our ſayd ſoueraygne lorde, that ſhall be ſo founden by the Iuſtices of peace in their ſeſſions, &amp; the forfaiture found in euery leete to be to the lorde of the leete.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte concerninge clothes, called Veſſes, made in the county of Suffolke. Cap. xj.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Vmbly ſhewen vnto your highnes your true ſubiectes &amp; clothiers of your Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of ſuffolke, that where in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixte yere of your moſt noble reigne, it was &amp; is enacted amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges other thinges, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge making of cloth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons ſhall not put any cloth to ſale, which whan it is full wet, ſhall ſhrinke more than one yard in length, &amp; one quarter of a yard in bredth, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more part therof: and clothes called narrowes or ſtraits after the rate, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peine to forfaite for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery cloth otherwiſe put to ſale .vi.s.viij.d. &amp; beſide to deduct of his price for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, to be rebated to the bier therof as muche after the rate, as the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:176604:13"/>
cloth ſo otherwiſe put to ſale (beinge full wette) ſhalbe ſhronke more than one yarde of that it was in lengthe, time of the ſame ſale, and as it ſhall (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge wette) lacke of the bread of one yarde &amp; three quarters of a yard. And in the ſame act was and is a prouiſo made, after the forme folowing.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwaye, that this acte extende not to wollen clothes, called kendalles, nor clothes called carpenell whytes, commonly made for lyning of hoſen, nor to any clothes called Toſtockes, made in the countye of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhyre, nor to any wollen clothes made in the county of Cornewall, nor for any Cottons or plaine lininge or friſe, made or to bee made in wales, Lancaſſhyre, and Cheſſhyre, or any of them.</p>
               <p>So it is moſte gracious ſoueraigne lorde, that Veſſes, otherwiſe called Set clothes of diuers colours, be made in your ſayde county of Suffolke which be made to be worne, and be worne in farre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis, &amp; not in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and be of ſmall prices not aboue xl.s. a clothe, that doe not holde the length nor breadth whan they be wet, which the byers do know wel wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they bie them, ſo that therin is no deceite. which clothes in the thirde yeare of the reigne of your moſt noble father kinge Henry the ſeuenth, were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for, ſo that they might lawfully be ſolde without any penalty or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayture, though they lacked in length or breadth whan they were full wet and ſo they haue vſed to do time out of minde.</p>
               <p>And in the prouiſo made in the ſayde acte of the ſixte yeare of youre moſte noble reygne they were forgetten &amp; not prouided for, which ſhould be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter impoueryſhinges of the clothiers of your ſayde county, and all other that be wrought by reaſon of clothe makinge wythin the ſayde countye of Suffolke, if no remedy ſhould be therfore prouided.</p>
               <p>Wherefore your humble ſubiectes humbly beſeech your highnes, that it be enacted by all the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and all the commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, with your moſt royall aſſente to the ſame: that all clothes called Veſſes, otherwiſe called Sette clothes, what colour ſo euer they be of, not beynge aboue the value of .xl.s. a clothe, ſhall not be forfait, for that they lacke in length &amp; breadth whan they be full wet after the iale of them afore this time made or hereafter be made. The ſayd act made in the ſixte yere of your moſt noble reigne, or any other acte here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore made to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>An act concerning coiners, that ſhall coine and make any money at any mint within this realme of Englande. Ca. xij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by the kynge our ſoueraigne lorde, and the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled, and by auctoritye of the ſame: that all ſuche coiners, as ſhall coyne and make any money at any mint with in thys Realme of Englande, ſhall make and coyne of euerye hundred poundes woorthe of Goolde, that they ſhall ſtrycke into coyne
<pb facs="tcp:176604:14"/>
xx.li. in the coyne of halfe angelles, commonly called peeces of golde of .xl.d. And of euery hundred poundes worthe of Bullyon, Plate, or Siluer, that they ſhall ſtrike into coyne, as many grotes as ſhall amount to the ſumme of fifty poundes ſterlinge: as many halfe grotes called pence of two pence, as ſhall amounte to the ſumme of .xx.li. ſterlinge: as many pence as ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounte to the ſumme of .xx.li. as many halfe pence as ſhall amount to the ſumme of ten markes ſterling and as many farthinges as amount to the ſumme of fiue markes ſterlinge. And that at any time that any coyners, in any minte within this realme, ſhall doe contrarye to thys acte, the maiſter and keper of that minte, for the time beinge, ſhall forfayte and loſe .x.li. The one moity thereof to be to the king our ſoueraygne lorde. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other moyty to the party that ſhall ſue for the ſame, by bill, information, action of debte, or otherwiſe: wherein the ſayd maiſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er ſhall not be admitted to do his law, &amp; no protection ne Eſſoyne to be allowed for the defendant.</p>
               <p>And for as muche as at this preſent time Farthinges and halfe pence be ſtriken all with one coyne, ſo that the common people of the realme manye times take theſe that be farthinges for halfe pence. Be it therefore enacted by the auctority aforeſayde, that all ſuche farthinges (that from henceforth ſhalbe made wythin this realme) ſhall haue vppon the one ſyde thereof the print of the port colice, and vpon the other ſide thereof the print of the Roſe with acroſſe, vpon like peine.</p>
               <p>And furthermore be it enacted by the auctority aforeſayde, that all maner perſons refortinge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd mint with any plate or bullion, vnder the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue aboueſayd, to be coyned, ſhall haue and receiue at the ſaid mint y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenth parte of all ſuch plate and bullion in halfe pence and farthinges.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway, that this acte or any thinge conteined in the ſame, be not in any wiſe preiudiciall to the Coyners, and minte maiſters of Yorke, Dureſme, and Canterbury, ne to any of them, for any money to be coyned there, other than heretofore hath bene accuſtomed. This acte to beginne to take effect at the feaſt of ſainct Michaell the archaungell next commynge, and not before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An act co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge the hauen and porte of Southampton. Ca. xiij.</head>
               <p>WHere in aparliament holden at weſtmin. the .xiiij. day of Octobre, the .xj. yere of the reigne of king Henry the .vij amongs other it was ordeined, eſtabliſhed, and enacted by the kinge our ſoueraigne lorde. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the aſſent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſpirytuall and temporall &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commons in the ſame parliamente aſſembled, for the reformation &amp; remedy of the decay of the hauen and port of Southampton, had by reaſon of diuers weres &amp; ingins for fyſhynge, made &amp; leuied in the ſame hauen, betweene a certaine place called Calſhare, and another place called Reedbridge, that it ſhould be lawefull to euery man to abate, plucke, &amp; take
<pb facs="tcp:176604:14"/>
away all and euery of the ſaid weres and ingins, at all times at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, being in the ſayd hauen, betwene the ſayd places, called Calſhare and Reedbridge, directly, without trouble, let, or vexation of any man, wyth diuers penalties and forfaytures to all ſuche perſons as hereafter ſhoulde make or leuye any ſuch weares or ingins, as in the ſame act more plainely may appere: The which act was made to endure only the ſpace of .xx. yeres than next enſuyng, during which act the ſayd weres and ingins were pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe, and the ſayd hauen greatly amended, to the ſuccour and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of all the marchauntes there reſortinge, the which yeres be now expired &amp; paſte, and the ſame act in no force by the ſpace of .vii yeres now paſſed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng which .vii. yeres diuers newe weres, gores, ſtackes, and ingins haue bene leuied and enhaunſed, by reaſon wherof, the ſayd hauen is greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied againe, and likely to be loſt for euer, to the kinges diſheriſon, &amp; hurte of the common weth of all thoſe parties if remedy therefore be not ſhortly had and prouided: wherfore be it now enacted by auctority of this preſent parliament, that the ſame acte and euery thinge therein conteined, ſhall be from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth good and effectuall accordinge to the purporte and entent of the ſame, and to continue for euer.</p>
               <p>And furthermore be it enacted, that euery owner, fermer, &amp; occupier of the ſayd weres, gores, and ingins, and euery of the ſame, do puldowne and put awaye the ſame, a this ſide the feaſt of ſaincte Michaell tharchaungell next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, without leuiyng, mainteining, making, or repayringe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame from henceforth, vppon peine of a hundred pounde, to be forfaited &amp; leuied likewiſe &amp; in like maner, as in the ſame former act is conteined. This acte to endure for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte concerninge ſuche as be in the kinges warres o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer or vpon the ſea. Cap. xiiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kynge our ſoueraygne Lorde of hys moſt bleſſed dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition well conſideringe, that nowe he is broughte into Warre of neceſſity with his auncient enemies, the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che kinge and the Scottes, and hathe had and ſhall haue dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the humble ſeruice in hys ſayde Warres, as well of hys nobles as other hys true ſubiectes: of his mooſte eſpeciall grace and benigne fauour, that he beareth vnto his ſayde ſubiectes, and for theyr more ſuretye and profyte, and for other reaſonable conſiderations hym eſpecially mouinge, by the aſſent of hys Lordes ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliamente aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by auctoritye of the ſame hathe enacted, ordeined and eſtabliſhed that euerye perſon and perſons, of what degree or condicion hee be of, that ſhall paſſe ouer the ſea, or that abideth vppon the ſea, or beyonde the ſea, and be in the kings wages or ſeruice of warre at this time, or hereafter ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:176604:15"/>
in any other place durynge his ſayd warres in ſeruice of warre, that euery of them, which haue lands &amp; tenements holden of the kinge or any other to their only vſe, ſhall now lawfully make therof alienation, feoffements and tranſmutacion of poſſeſſion, by dede or dedes, fine or fines, recouerye or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coueries, for the perfourmaunce of his or their will or willes, without any fine or fines, for the ſaid alienations, feoffements, fines, recoueries, or tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutacion of poſſeſſion therfore, or for any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be made: And that thei and euery of them, their heires &amp; aſſignes, &amp; the heires &amp; aſſignes of euerye of them, by auctority of this preſente acte, be diſcharged of all &amp; euery ſuche fines, without letters pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or other diſcharge in that behalfe. And furthermore be it alſo ordeined and enacted, by the ſayd auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority, that if any perſon or perſons, ſo beinge in the ſayde ſeruice of warre, which hold lands, tenements, or hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the kyng or of any other by knightes ſeruice or otherwyſe, wherefore his heyre or heyres oughte or might be in warde, &amp; fortune in the ſayd ſeruice to deceaſe beyond the ſea or vpon the ſea, or els where, in the ſeruice of the kinge in his warres againſt his enemies, or that any feoffement of the ſame landes and tenements, be ſuppoſed to be made by colluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heire or heires of the owner of the ſame lands &amp; tenements being within age: that than the feoffees or executours of euery ſuch perſon &amp; perſons ſo deceaſed, haue the warde and mariage of the heire or heires, ſo being within age, vntill they come to their full &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full age. And the landes and tenementes, and other hereditaments ſo hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, during the nonage of euery ſuch heire or heires to the perfourmaunce of the wil of the ſayd perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo deceaſed without any accompt or ſommes of money, or other thinge therefore to be yelden, payinge therout yerely the rentes of the chiefe lorde or lordes of the fee of the ſame, ſauinge to euerye perſon or perſons, other then the ſayde perſon or perſons, that ſhal make any ſuch alienation, feoffement, fine, or ſuffer recouery to be had againſt him, without paying therefore any fine to the kinge, or the lorde or lordes (of whom the ſayde landes be holden) for the ſame ſuche right, tytle, vſe, and intereſt, as they had before the ſaid feoffement, alienation, fine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery, or tranſmutacion of poſſeſſion, or any of them made or ſuffered of any ſuch lands, tenements, or hereditamentes, wherof any ſuch feoffeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, fine, recouery or alienation ſo ſhall be made. Prouided alwayes, that thys act extend not to any capitaine or capitaines, ſouldiour or ſouldiours, that now be or hereafter ſhall be reteygned wythin the townes of Calis, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Guines, Riſebanke, Berwike, Wales, or any of them, or marches of the ſame. Excepte they or any of them procede in army royall againſte the kynges enemyes.</p>
               <closer>God ſaue the king.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
